Register of the E. E. Gopshtein Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
E. E. Gopshtein papers,
1916-1981
93068
Gopshtein, E. E.
9 manuscript boxes (3.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diaries, and historical, biographical and bibliographical writings, relating to the history of the Crimea, especially during the period from the Russian Revolution to the 1950s; the history of publishing in the Crimea during this period; notable persons of the Crimea, especially artists; the Jewish community of Simferopol'; and the German occupation of Simferopol' during World War II. Includes some later correspondence relating to the writings of E. E. Gopshtein.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (14 reels).
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1885 Born, Simferopol, Crimea
Before 1917 Worked for an insurance company and for the Azov-Don Bank
1917-1918 Manager, Finance Department, City of Simferopol
1918 Manager, Crimean Communal Bank
1941 December 11 – 1944 April 13 Lived in a hiding place during the German occupation of Simferopol
1960 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Evsei Efimovich Gopshtein were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993 from his granddaughter Margaret A. Hopstein and from Leonid Hmelevsky, III. They represent only part of his archives, as some papers were destroyed during World War II and others are in Moscow. As for the very large library on the Crimea that Gopshtein had collected, it was stolen during the war.
Gopshtein was the only one out of 14,000 Jews in Simferopol to survive the killings and deportations when his city came under German occupation, hiding as he did in the one-room apartment of a friend for twenty-eight months. (Gopshtein had asked for her help because he had hidden her cousin, a White Russian Vrangel army officer, from the Bolsheviks some twenty years before.) An account of that experience, as well as an interview he gave in August 1944, can be found in the biographical file. Also important are Gopshtein's diaries, of which the Archives holds those parts that cover the war period.
But the bulk of the collection consists of his bibliographical work and writings. Gopshtein was an avid bibliographer and historian, and compiled many bibliographies of publications relating to the history and people of the Crimea, primarily to its Jewish population.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Ukraine--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Publishers and publishing--Ukraine--Crimea.; Crimea (Ukraine)--Biography.; Art--Ukraine--Crimea.; Jews--Ukraine--Simferopol'.; Simferopol' (Ukraine)--History.; World War, 1939-1945--Ukraine--Simferopol'.; Ukraine--History--German occupation, 1941-1944.; Ukraine.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945.; Crimea (Ukraine)--History.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1944-1981. (Box 1)
  Biographical account, clippings, correspondence, and interview, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Diaries, 1938-1953. (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically
- Bibliographies, 1930-1957? (Box 2-6)
  Bibliographies of publications on the history and people of the Crimea, arranged first by city and region of publication and then chronologically by title of bibliography
- Writings, 1916-1937? (Box 7-9)
  Articles, drafts of unpublished books, and histories, arranged chronologically by title
- Photographs, 1928. (Box 9)
  Six prints depicting different Jewish religious symbols and a fragment of a Synagogue
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1944-1981 (Box 1)
  - Biographical account of Gopshtein's life in Simferopol during the German occupation of the city, 1941-1944, published in The Black Book: The Ruthless Murder of Jews by German-Fascist Invaders Throughout the Temporarily-Occupied Regions of the Soviet Union and in the Death Campus of Poland During the War 1941-1945, Holocaust Library, New York, 1981, pp. 369-372. (Folder 1: 1)
    Printed copy of English and Russian versions
  - Clippings, 1956-1959 (Folder 1: 2-3)
  - Correspondence between Gopshtein's son, Aleksander E. Gopshtein, and the Krymskaia Oblastnaia Biblioteka (Crimea Region Library), relating to the disposal of E. E. Gopshtein's writings, 1965-1975 (Folder 1: 4-5)
  - Interview, Simferopol, 1944 August 16. (Folder 1: 6)
    Typescript
- DIARIES, 1938-1953.
  "Iz starykh bumag: Obryvki zapisok simferopolskogo obyvatelia, sovremennika sovetskoi vlasti i Vtoroi mirovoi voiny" (From Old Papers: Scrap Notes of a Simferopol Inhabitant, Contemporary of Soviet Power and World War II). Holograph
  - 1938-1942 (part 3) (Folder 1: 7-9)
  - 1943-1953 (part 4) (Folder 1: 10)
  - 1943-1953 (part 4) (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
- BIBLIOGRAPHIES, 1930-1957?
  - General
    - General. (Folder 2: 4)
      Indexes of Gopshtein's bibliographies, 1930-1954
    - Military publications, 1933 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Serials, 1942-1944
      - General (Folder 2: 6-8)
      - Cities
        - Alushta (Folder 2: 9-10)
        - Balaklava (Folder 2: 11-12)
        - Bakhchisarai (Folder 2: 13-14)
        - Dzhankoi (Folder 2: 15-16)
        - Evpatoriia (Folder 2: 17-18)
        - Feodosiia (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
        - Karasubazar (Folder 3: 3-4)
        - Kerch (Folder 3: 5)
        - Sevastopol (Folder 3: 6-7)
        - Simferopol (Folder 3: 8-10)
        - Staryi Krym (Folder 3: 11-12)
        - Yalta (Folder 3: 13-14)
      - Regions
        - Ak-Mechetskii (Folder 3: 15)
        - Biiuk-Onlarskii (Folder 3: 16)
        - Fraidovskii (Folder 3: 17)
        - Ichkerskii (Folder 3: 18)
        - Ishunskii (Folder 3: 19)
        - Kalaiskii (Folder 3: 20)
        - Kirovskii (Folder 3: 21)
        - Krasno-Perekopskii (Folder 3: 22)
        - Kuibyshevskii (Folder 3: 23)
        - Larindorfskii (Folder 3: 24)
        - Leninskii (Folder 3: 25)
        - Maiak-Salynskii (Folder 3: 26)
        - Sakskii (Folder 3: 27)
        - Seitlerskii (Folder 3: 28)
        - Sudakskii (Box-folder 4: 1)
        - Telmanskii (Folder 4: 2)
        - Zuiskii (Folder 4: 3)
    - Unpublished works (Folder 4: 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 4: 5)
  - "Liudi Kryma: Alfavitnyi perechen biograficheskikh i bibliograficheskikh dannykh" (Alphabetical List of Biographical and Bibliographic Data on People of the Crimea), n.d. (Folder 4: 6-13)
    Holograph
  - "Liudi Kryma: Alfavitnyi perechen biograficheskikh i bibliograficheskikh dannykh" (Alphabetical List of Biographical and Bibliographic Data on People of the Crimea), n.d. (Box-folder 5: 1-7)
  - "Liudi Kryma: Alfavitnyi perechen biograficheskikh i bibliograficheskikh dannykh" (Alphabetical List of Biographical and Bibliographic Data on People of the Crimea), n.d. (Box-folder 6: 1-4)
  - "Ob odnoi staroi knige: Bibliograficheskaia zametka" (About an Old Book: Bibliographical Note), 1928. (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Istoriko-bibliograficheskoe opisanie statistiko-ekonomicheskikh obsledovanii byvshei Tavricheskoi gubernii i Kryma: Konets 18 veka, 19 i pervoe desiatiletie 20 veka" (Historical Description of the Statistical Economic Research of the Former Tavriia Region and the Crimea), 1954. (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Bibliografiia istorii revoliutsionnogo dvizheniia i sobytii pervoi i vtoroi rossiiskikh revoliutsii v Krymu, " (History of the Revolutionary Movement and Events of the First and Second Russian Revolutions in the Crimea, 1830-1957), 1957? (Folder 6: 7-8)
- WRITINGS, 1916-1937? (Box 7)
  - "Grifony v iskusstve sinagog Kryma: K ikonografii tavricheskikh sinagog" (Elements of Biblical Archeology in the Arts of Tavriia Synagogues), n.d. (Folder 7: 1)
  - "Na starom evreiskom kladbishche v Simferopole vesnoi 1934 goda" (In the Old Jewish Cemetery in Simferopol in Spring of 1934), n.d. (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Pogovorki, poslovitsy, rugan i prokliatiia evreiskogo naseleniia goroda Simferopolia: K materialam po folkloru evreev v SSSR" (Sayings, Proverbs, and Swear Phrases of the Jewry in the City of Simferopol before World War I: Materials on the Folklore of Jews in the USSR), n.d. (Folder 7: 3)
  - "Evreiskie narodnye kartinki" (Jewish Folk Pictures), Jewish Life, 1916 July 31. (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Revolutsiia v Krymu: Epizodicheskaia khronika, v ocherkakh i nastroeniiakh voennoi, obshchestvenno-politicheskoi, kulturnoi i bytovoi zhizni v Krymu v gody revolutsii" (History of the Russian Revolution in the Crimea, 1917-1937), 1937? (parts 1 and 2) (Folder 7: 5-10)
  - "Revolutsiia v Krymu: Epizodicheskaia khronika, v ocherkakh i nastroeniiakh voennoi, obshchestvenno-politicheskoi, kulturnoi i bytovoi zhizni v Krymu v gody revolutsii" (History of the Russian Revolution in the Crimea, 1917-1937), 1937? (parts 1 and 2) (Box-folder 8: 1-5)
  - "Revolutsiia v Krymu: Epizodicheskaia khronika, v ocherkakh i nastroeniiakh voennoi, obshchestvenno-politicheskoi, kulturnoi i bytovoi zhizni v Krymu v gody revolutsii" (History of the Russian Revolution in the Crimea, 1917-1937), 1937? (parts 1 and 2) (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1928
  - 2 photographs depicting different Jewish religious symbols made out of wood and iron (Folder 9: 3)
  - 4 photographs depicting one fragment of a Synagogue (Folder 9: 4)